So, I was just asked to go and shoot this film called "Elizabeth."
إذا، طلب مني الذهاب لتصوير فيلم يسمى "إليزابيث".
And we're all talking about this great English icon and saying,
وكنا نناقش هذه الأيقونة الإنجليزية العظيمة قائلين:
"She's a fantastic woman, she does everything.
"إنها امرأة رائعة. لقد عملت كل شيء.
How are we going to introduce her?"
كيف سنقوم بتقديمها؟"
So we went around the table with the studio and the producers and the writer,
كنا جالسين إلى الطاولة في الاستوديو مع المنتجين والكاتب،
and they came to me and said, "Shekhar, what do you think?"
وسألوني، "شيكار، ما رأيك؟"
And I said, "I think she's dancing."
وأجبتهم: "أعتقد أنها ترقص."
And I could see everybody looked at me,
رأيت الجميع ينظر إلي،
somebody said, "Bollywood."
وقال أحدهم: "[أسلوب] بوليوود."
The other said, "How much did we hire him for?"
وقال آخر، "كم هو أجره؟"
And the third said, "Let's find another director."
وقال ثالث: "لنجد مخرجا آخر."
I thought I had better change.
فكرت أن علي تغيير الفكرة.
So we had a lot of discussion on how to introduce Elizabeth,
ولهذا ناقشنا مطولا طريقة تقديم إليزابيث،
and I said, "OK, maybe I am too Bollywood.
وقلت، حسنا، ربما أنا مشبع بأسلوب الأفلام الهندية.
Maybe Elizabeth, this great icon, dancing?
ربما إليزابيث، هذه الأيقونة، ترقص؟
What are you talking about?"
مالذي تقوله؟
So I rethought the whole thing,
ولهذا أعدت التفكير في الموضوع كله،
and then we all came to a consensus.
وبعدها توصلنا إلى قرار بالإجماع.
And here was the introduction of this
وهذه هي مقدمة فلم هذه
great British icon called "Elizabeth."
الأيقونة البريطانية العظيمة المسماة "إليزابيث".
Leicester: May I join you, my lady?
ليسيستر: أتسمحين لي برفقتك، سيدتي؟
Elizabeth: If it please you, sir.
إليزابيث: إذا رغبت، سيدي.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Shekhar Kapur: So she was dancing.
شيكار كابور: إذن كانت ترقص.
So how many people who saw the film did not get
إذن كم من الأشخاص الذين شاهدوا الفلم لم يفهموا
that here was a woman in love,
أن هذه امرأة غارقة في الحب،
that she was completely innocent
وأنها تتسم بالبراءة
and saw great joy in her life, and she was youthful?
وترى روعة الحياة أمامها، وأنها شابة.
And how many of you did not get that?
كم منكم لم يفهموا ذلك؟
That's the power of visual storytelling,
هذه هي قوة السرد القصصي المرئي
that's the power of dance, that's the power of music:
هذه القوة الكامنة في الرقص. هذه قوة الموسيقى.
the power of not knowing.
قوة عدم المعرفة.
When I go out to direct a film,
عندما أباشر إخراج فيلم
every day we prepare too much, we think too much.
نبالغ في التحضيرات، ونفكر كثيرا في التفاصيل.
Knowledge becomes a weight upon wisdom.
وعندها تثقل المعرفة كاهل الحكمة.
You know, simple words lost
أتعلمون، تضيع الكلمات البسيطة
in the quicksand of experience.
في الرمال المتحركة للخبرة.
So I come up, and I say,
وعليه أنا آتي وأقول،
"What am I going to do today?" I'm not going to do what I planned to do,
"مالذي سأفعله اليوم؟" لن أفعل ما خططت له،
and I put myself into absolute panic.
وعندها أصبح في حال فزع مطلق.
It's my one way of getting rid of my mind,
وهذه طريقتي في التخلص من عقلي،
getting rid of this mind that says,
التخلص من هذا العقل الذي يكرر علي،
"Hey, you know what you're doing. You know exactly what you're doing.
"أنت تعرف ما أنت فاعل. أنت تعرف تماما ماذا تفعل.
You're a director, you've done it for years."
أنت مخرج، تقوم بهذا لسنوات."
So I've got to get there
لهذا يجب أن أصل إلى هناك
and be in complete panic.
وأكون في حال فزع مطبق.
It's a symbolic gesture. I tear up the script,
في إشارة رمزية، أنا أقوم بتمزيق النص.
I go and I panic myself, I get scared.
أنا أُفزع نفسي. يصيبني الخوف.
I'm doing it right now; you can watch me. I'm getting nervous,
أنا أقوم بذلك الآن. أنتم تنظرون إلي. أنا أشعر بالتوتر.
I don't know what to say, I don't know what I'm doing, I don't want to go there.
لا أعرف ماذا أقول. لا أعرف ماذا افعل. لا أريد أن أذهب إلى هناك.
And as I go there, of course, my A.D. says,
وأثناء ذهابي هناك، بالطبع، يقول لي مساعد المخرج،
"You know what you're going to do, sir." I say, "Of course I do."
"أنت تعرف مالذي ستقوم به يا سيدي،" وأجيب "أكيد."
And the studio executives, they would say,
ويقول مدراء التنفيذ في الاستوديو،
"Hey, look at Shekhar. He's so prepared."
"انظروا إلى شيكر. إنه مستعد تماما."
And inside I've just been listening to Nusrat Fateh Ali Khan
ولكن في الداخل أكون أستمع إلى نصرت فاتح علي خان
because he's chaotic.
لأنه فوضوي.
I'm allowing myself to go into chaos
وأسمح لنفسي بالولوج إلى الفوضى
because out of chaos, I'm hoping some moments of truth will come.
لأنه من رحم الفوضى، أرجو أن تنبثق لحظات من الحقيقية.
All preparation is preparation.
كل التحضيرات تبقى تحضيرات.
I don't even know if it's honest.
لا أعرف إن كانت صادقة.
I don't even know if it's truthful.
لا أعرف إن كانت حقيقية.
The truth of it all comes on the moment, organically,
حقيقة كل شيء تأتي وليدة اللحظة ذاتها.
and if you get five great moments
وإذا نلت خمس لحظات عظيمة
of great, organic stuff
من الأمور الرائعة وليدة تلك اللحظات
in your storytelling, in your film,
في سرد قصتك، في فيلمك،
your film, audiences will get it.
فإن مشاهدي فيلمك سوف يفهمونه.
So I'm looking for those moments, and I'm standing there
لهذا فأنا أبحث عن هذه اللحظات، وأنا أقف هناك
and saying, "I don't know what to say."
وأقول، أنا لا أعرف ماذا أقول.
So, ultimately, everybody's looking at you,
لهذا، في نهاية الأمر الجميع ينظر إليك،
200 people at seven in the morning
200 شخص في السابعة صباحا،
who got there at quarter to seven, and you arrived at seven,
لقد وصلوا في السابعة إلا ربعا، في حين تصل أنت في السابعة،
and everybody's saying,
والجميع يقول،
"Hey. What's the first thing? What's going to happen?"
"هيه، بماذا سنبدأ؟ ماذا سيحصل؟"
And you put yourself into a state of panic
عندها تضع نفسك في حالة من الفزع
where you don't know, and so you don't know.
في مكان مجهول، حيث أنت لا تعرف.
And so, because you don't know,
ولهذا ولأنك لا تعرف،
you're praying to the universe because you're praying to the universe
فأنت تباشر الدعاء لأنك بحاجة إلى ذلك
that something -- I'm going to try and access the universe
الشيء، لهذا فأنا أبدء بمحاولة الوصول إلى الكون
the way Einstein -- say a prayer --
على طريقة أينشتاين، يبدأ بالدعاء،
accessed his equations,
يتوصل إلى معادلاته،
the same source. I'm looking for the same source
إنه المصدر ذاته، فأنا أبحث عن المصدر نفسه
because creativity comes from absolutely the same source
لأن الإبداع يأتي من المصدر ذاته
that you meditate somewhere outside yourself,
فأنت عندما تتامل في مكان خارج ذاتك،
outside the universe.
خارج الكون.
You're looking for something that comes and hits you.
فأنت تبحث عن شيء ما ليأتي ويتكشف لك.
Until that hits you, you're not going to do the first shot.
وإلى أن يتكشف لك ذلك، فأنت لن تقوم بالرمية الأولى,
So what do you do?
إذن ماذا يتعين عليك فعله؟
So Cate says, "Shekhar, what do you want me to do?"
ولهذا تسألني كيت، "شيكر، ماذا تريد مني أن أفعل؟"
And I say, "Cate, what do you want to do?" (Laughter)
وأقول: "كيت، ماذا تريدين أنتِ أن تفعلي؟" (ضحك)
"You're a great actor, and I like to give to my actors --
"أنت ممثلة رائعة، وأنا أحب السماع من ممثلي.
why don't you show me what you want to do?"
لماذا لا تريني ما تريدين فعله."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What am I doing? I'm trying to buy time.
مذا أفعل؟ أنا أحاول كسب الوقت.
I'm trying to buy time.
أحاول كسب الوقت.
So the first thing about storytelling that I learned,
لهذا فأول شيء تعلمته عن سرد القصة،
and I follow all the time is: Panic.
وهو ما أفعله طوال الوقت، هو الفزع.
Panic is the great access of creativity
فالفزع هو بطاقة الدخول إلى الإبداع
because that's the only way to get rid of your mind.
لأنه الطريقة الوحيدة التي تتخلص به من عقلك.
Get rid of your mind.
تخلص من عقلك.
Get out of it, get it out.
اخرج منه. تخلص منه.
And let's go to the universe because
ولنتجه إلى الكون لأنه
there's something out there that is more
يحتوي على شيء أكثر
truthful than your mind,
صدقا من عقلك،
that is more truthful than your universe.
وأكثر صدقا من عالمك.
[unclear], you said that yesterday. I'm just repeating it
(غير واضح)، أنت قلت ذلك البارحة. وأنا أكرره
because that's what I follow constantly
لأن هذا ما أتبعه دوما
to find the shunyata somewhere, the emptiness.
لأجد "الشونياتا" في مكان ما، الفراغ.
Out of the emptiness comes a moment of creativity.
ومن الفراغ تأتي لحظة الإبداع.
So that's what I do.
وهذا ما أفعله.
When I was a kid -- I was about eight years old.
عندما كنت صغيرا، في حوالي الثامنة من العمر.
You remember how India was. There was no pollution.
تذكرون كيف كانت الهند. لم يكن هناك تلوث.
In Delhi, we used to live -- we used to call it a chhat or the khota.
في دلهي، حيث كنا نعيش، كنا ندعوها "كوتا" أو الكوتا.
Khota's now become a bad word. It means their terrace --
واليوم أصبحت هذه الكلمة تعبيرا سيئا. وتعني شرفتهم،
and we used to sleep out at night.
وكنا ننام هناك ليلا.
At school I was being just taught about physics,
في المدرسة كنت بدأت أتعلم الفيزياء،
and I was told that
وقد قيل لي
if there is something that exists,
أنه إن كان هناك ما يوجد
then it is measurable.
فمن الممكن قياسه.
If it is not measurable,
وإذا لم يكن من الممكن قياسه،
it does not exist.
فهو غير موجود.
And at night I would lie out, looking at the unpolluted sky,
وفي الليل كنت أستلقي ناظرا إلى السماء الصافية
as Delhi used to be at that time when I was a kid,
فوق دلهي في ذلك الوقت عندما كنت طفلا،
and I used to stare at the universe and say,
وكنت أحدق في الكون وأقول،
"How far does this universe go?"
"إلى أين يمتد هذا الكون؟"
My father was a doctor.
كان والدي طبيبا.
And I would think, "Daddy, how far does the universe go?"
وكنت أفكر، "بابا، إلى أين يمتد هذا الكون؟"
And he said, "Son, it goes on forever."
وكان يجيبني، " يا بني، إنه يمتد إلى مالا نهاية."
So I said, "Please measure forever
وكنت أخبره: "أرجوك قِس اللانهاية
because in school they're teaching me
ففي المدرسة يعلموننا
that if I cannot measure it, it does not exist.
أن ما لا نستطيع قياسه فهو غير موجود.
It doesn't come into my frame of reference."
وهو لا يندرج ضمن الإطار المرجعي لي."
So, how far does eternity go?
إذن إلى أين تمتد الأبدية؟
What does forever mean?
ماذا يعني (تعبير) إلى الأبد؟
And I would lie there crying at night
وكنت أستلقي باكيا في الليل
because my imagination could not touch creativity.
لأن مخيلتي لم تستطع الولوج إلى الإبداع.
So what did I do?
إذن ماذا فعلت؟
At that time, at the tender age of seven,
حينما كنت طريّ العود في السابعة من العمر،
I created a story.
لقد تخيلت قصة.
What was my story?
ماذا كانت قصتي؟
And I don't know why, but I remember the story.
وأنا لا أعرف لم، ولكني أتذكر القصة.
There was a woodcutter
كانت هناك حطاب
who's about to take his ax and chop a piece of wood,
على وشك تناول فأسه ليحطب قطعة من الخشب،
and the whole galaxy is one atom of that ax.
وكانت المجرة كلها في ذرة واحدة من تلك الفأس.
And when that ax hits that piece of wood,
وعندما ضربت الفأس قطعة الخشب،
that's when everything will destroy
عندها سيدمر كل شي
and the Big Bang will happen again.
ويحصل الانفجار الكبير ثانيةً.
But all before that there was a woodcutter.
ولكن قبل كل ذلك كان هناك حطاب.
And then when I would run out of that story,
وعندما كنت أستهلك هذه القصة،
I would imagine that woodcutter's universe
كنت أتخيل أن عالم الحطاب
is one atom in the ax of another woodcutter.
هو ذرة واحدة في فأس حطاب آخر.
So every time, I could tell my story again and again
وهكذا كنت أكرر قصتي مرات ومرات
and get over this problem,
متجاوزا هذه المشكلة،
and so I got over the problem.
وبهذا تجاوزت هذه المشكلة.
How did I do it? Tell a story.
كيف فعلت ذلك؟ برواية قصة.
So what is a story?
إذن ماهي القصة؟
A story is our -- all of us --
إنها قصتنا جميعا.
we are the stories we tell ourselves.
فنحن القصص التي نرويها لأنفسنا.
In this universe, and this existence,
في هذا الكون، وفي هذا الوجود،
where we live with this duality
حيث نعيش مع هذه الثنائية
of whether we exist or not
هل نحن موجودون أم لا
and who are we,
ومن نحن،
the stories we tell ourselves are the stories
فالقصص التي نرويها لأنفسنا
that define the potentialities
هي التي تحدد الاحتمالات الكامنة
of our existence.
لوجودنا.
We are the stories we tell ourselves.
نحن القصص التي نرويها لأنفسنا.
So that's as wide as we look at stories.
إذن هذا ما يخص نظرتنا للقصص.
A story is the relationship
فالقصة هي علاقة
that you develop between who you are,
تطورها بين من تكون،
or who you potentially are,
أو من قد تكون،
and the infinite world, and that's our mythology.
والعالم لامتناهي الاحتمالات، وهذه هي أسطورتنا.
We tell our stories,
نقوم بسرد قصصنا،
and a person without a story does not exist.
والشخص الذي لا قصة له لا وجود له.
So Einstein told a story
إذن روى آينشتاين قصة
and followed his stories and came up with theories
واتبع قصصه إلى أن توصل إلى نظرياته
and came up with theories and then came up with his equations.
وبعد أن توصل إلى نظرياته توصل إلى معادلاته.
Alexander had a story that his mother used to tell him,
ألكساندر كانت لديه قصة ترويها له والدته،
and he went out to conquer the world.
وبهذا خرج ليقهر العالم.
We all, everybody, has a story that they follow.
نحن جميعا، لدينا قصة لنحققها.
We tell ourselves stories.
نحن نروي القصص لأنفسنا.
So, I will go further, and I say,
ولهذا سأذهب أبعد من ذلك وأقول،
"I tell a story, and therefore I exist."
أنا أروي قصة، إذن أنا موجود.
I exist because there are stories,
أنا موجود بسبب وجود القصص،
and if there are no stories, we don't exist.
وإذا لم تكن القصص موجودة، إذن أنا غير موجود.
We create stories to define our existence.
فنحن نخلق القصص التي تحدد وجودنا.
If we do not create the stories,
وإذا لم نخلق القصص،
we probably go mad.
فقد يصيبنا الجنون.
I don't know; I'm not sure, but that's what I've done all the time.
لا أعلم. ولست متاكدا، ولكن هذا ما أفعله طوال الوقت.
Now, a film.
الآن، الفيلم.
A film tells a story.
الفيلم يروي قصة.
I often wonder when I make a film -- I'm thinking of making a film of the Buddha --
أتساءل عندما أصنع فيلما، أفكر أن أصنع فيلما عن بوذا،
and I often wonder: If Buddha had all the elements
وغالبا ما اتساءل، إذا توفرت كافة العناصر لبوذا
that are given to a director --
كتلك المتوفرة للمخرج،
if he had music, if he had visuals, if he had a video camera --
إذا كان لديه موسيقى، والمؤثرات المرئية، وكاميرا الفيديو،
would we get Buddhism better?
هل سنفهم البوذية بشكل أفضل؟
But that puts some kind of burden on me.
ولكن هذا يثقل كاهلي.
I have to tell a story
فانا يجب أن أروي قصة
in a much more elaborate way,
بطريقة أكثر تفصيلا،
but I have the potential.
ولكن لدي الإمكانية.
It's called subtext.
وهو يدعى النص الباطن.
When I first went to Hollywood, they said --
عندما ذهبت إلى هوليود أول مرة، قالوا لي
I used to talk about subtext, and my agent came to me,
وكنت أتكلم عن النص الباطن، وكان وكيلي يأتيني،
"Would you kindly not talk about subtext?"
ويقول"هلا توقفت عن الحديث عن النص الباطن؟"
And I said, "Why?" He said, "Because nobody is going to give you a film
وسألته "لماذا؟" وقال: "لأن أحدا لن يعطيك فيلما
if you talk about subtext.
إذا تحدثت عن النص الباطن.
Just talk about plot
تحدث فقط عن الحبكة
and say how wonderful you'll shoot the film,
وتحدث عن كم هو رائع أنك ستصور الفيلم
what the visuals will be."
وما ستكون عليه المؤثرات المرئية."
So when I look at a film,
ولهذا عندما أنظر إلى فيلم،
here's what we look for:
إليكم ما نبحث عنه،
We look for a story on the plot level,
نبحث عن قصة على مستوى الحبكة،
then we look for a story
ثم نبحث عن قصة
on the psychological level,
على المستوى النفسي،
then we look for a story on the political level,
ثم نبحث عن قصة على المستوى السياسي،
then we look at a story
ثم ننظر إلى قصة
on a mythological level.
على المستوى الأسطوري.
And I look for stories on each level.
وأنا أبحث عن القصص في كل مستوى.
Now, it is not necessary
الآن ليس بالضرورة
that these stories agree with each other.
أن تتفق هذه القصص معا.
What is wonderful is,
الأمر المدهش هو،
at many times, the stories will contradict with each other.
أنه في الكثير من الأحيان، تتناقض هذه القصص مع بعضها.
So when I work with Rahman who's a great musician,
لهذا عندما أعمل مع راهمان وهو موسيقي عظيم،
I often tell him, "Don't follow what the script already says.
كثيرا ما أقول له: "لا تتبع ما يقوله النص.
Find that which is not.
ابحث عن ما لا يقوله.
Find the truth for yourself,
ابحث عن الحقيقة بنفسك،
and when you find the truth for yourself,
وعندما تجد الحقيقة بنفسك،
there will be a truth in it, but it may contradict the plot,
ستحتمل الصواب، ولكنها قد تناقض الحبكة،
but don't worry about it."
ولكن لا تقلق على ذلك."
So, the sequel to "Elizabeth," "Golden Age."
إذن، الجزء الثاني من فيلم "إليزابيث"، "العصر الذهبي."
When I made the sequel to "Elizabeth," here was a story that
عندما عملت الجزء الثاني من "إليزابيث"، كان هناك القصة
the writer was telling:
التي يرويها الكاتب.
A woman who was threatened
قصة امرأة يتهددها
by Philip II
فيليب الثاني
and was going to war,
وكانت ستذهب إلى الحرب،
and was going to war, fell in love with Walter Raleigh.
وكانت ستدخل الحرب، ووقعت في حب والتر رالي.
Because she fell in love with Walter Raleigh,
ولأنها وقعت في حب والتر رالي،
she was giving up the reasons she was a queen,
كانت تتنازل عن ما كان يجعلها ملكة.
and then Walter Raleigh
بعدها والتر رالي
fell in love with her lady in waiting,
وقع في حب وصيفتها،
and she had to decide whether she was a queen going to war
وكان عليها أن تقرر فيما إذا كانت ملكة تذهب إلى الحرب
or she wanted...
أو كانت تريد ..
Here's the story I was telling:
إليكم القصة التي كنت أرويها.
The gods up there,
الآلهة هناك.
there were two people.
وهناك شخصين.
There was Philip II, who was divine
فيليب الثاني، الذي كان ربانيا
because he was always praying,
لأنه كان دائم الصلاة،
and there was Elizabeth, who was divine,
وهناك إليزابيث، التي كانت ربانية،
but not quite divine because she thought she was divine,
ولكن ليس تماما لأنها كانت تعتقد أنها ربانية،
but the blood of being mortal flowed in her.
ولكن دم البشر الفانين يسري في عروقها.
But the divine one was unjust,
ولكن الربانية كانت غير عادلة،
so the gods said,
ولهذا قال الأرباب،
"OK, what we need to do is
"حسنا. يجب علينا
help the just one."
أن نساعد تلك العادلة."
And so they helped the just one.
وبهذا ساعدوا (إليزابيث) العادلة.
And what they did was, they sent Walter Raleigh down
وما فعلوه هو أنهم أرسلوا والتر رالي
to physically separate her mortal self
ليفصل جسديا نفسها البشرية الفانية
from her spirit self.
عن روحها.
And the mortal self was the girl
وكانت الذات البشرية الفتاة
that Walter Raleigh was sent,
التي أرسل إليها والتر رالي
and gradually he separated her
وتدريجيا فصلها
so she was free to be divine.
لتصبح حرة وتصبح ربانية.
And the two divine people fought,
وبهذا تحارب الشخصين الربانيين،
and the gods were on the side of divinity.
وكانت الآلهة إلى جانب الألوهية.
Of course, all the British press got really upset.
بالطبع، كانت الصحافة البريطانية متضايقة جدا.
They said, "We won the Armada."
وقالوا: "لقد ربحنا حرب الأرمادا."
But I said, "But the storm won the Armada.
ولكني قلت: "ولكن العاصفة هي التي ربحتها.
The gods sent the storm."
والأرباب هم الذين أرسلوا العاصفة."
So what was I doing?
إذن ماذا كنت أفعل؟
I was trying to find a mythic reason
كنت أحاول أن أجد السبب الأسطوري
to make the film.
لصناعة الفيلم.
Of course, when I asked Cate Blanchett, I said, "What's the film about?"
بالطبع عندما سألت كيت بلانشت، قلت: "عن ماذا يحكي الفيلم؟"
She said, "The film's about a woman
قالت: "الفيلم عن امراة
coming to terms with growing older."
تقبل واقع أنها تقدمت بالسن."
Psychological.
المستوى النفسي.
The writer said "It's about history, plot."
الكاتب قال إنه عن التاريخ، الحبكة.
I said "It's about mythology,
أنا قلت أنه عن الأسطورة،
the gods."
عن الأرباب.
So let me show you a film --
إذن دعوني أعرض عليكم فيلما،
a piece from that film --
جزءا من فيلم --
and how a camera also --
وكيف اشتركت الكاميرا--
so this is a scene, where in my mind,
إذن هذا مشهد، حيث في ذهني،
she was at the depths of mortality.
تظهر أنها في قاع طبيعتها الفانية.
She was discovering what mortality actually means,
وهي تكتشف المعني الحقيقي للفناء،
and if she is at the depths of mortality,
وإذا كانت في أعماق بشريتها الفانية،
what really happens.
ماذا يحصل بالفعل.
And she's recognizing the dangers of mortality
لقد بدأت تستوعب مخاطر البشرية الفانية
and why she should break away from mortality.
ولماذا يتعين عليها الإفلات منها.
Remember, in the film, to me,
تذكروا، في الفيلم، بالنسبة لي
both her and her lady in waiting
كلتاهما هي ووصيفتها
were parts of the same body,
تكونان جسدا واحدا،
one the mortal self
الذات الفانية من ناحية
and one the spirit self.
والروح الباقية من ناحية اخرى.
So can we have that second?
إذن هل لنا بتلك الثانية؟
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Elizabeth: Bess?
إليزابيث: بيس؟
Bess?
بيس؟
Bess Throckmorton?
بيس ثروكمورتن؟
Bess: Here, my lady.
بيس: هنا، مولاتي.
Elizabeth: Tell me, is it true?
إليزابيث: أخبريني أهو صحيح؟
Are you with child?
هل أنت حامل؟
Bess: Yes, my lady.
بيس: أجل يا مولاتي.
Elizabeth: Traitorous.
إليزابيث: أيتها الخائنة.
You dare to keep secrets from me?
وتجرئين على إخفاء الأسرار عني؟
You ask my permission before you rut,
عليك طلب إذني قبل أن تتعفني
before you breed.
قبل أن تتناسلي.
My bitches wear my collars.
كلابي ترتدي أطواقي.
Do you hear me? Do you hear me?
أتسمعينني؟ أتسمعينني؟
Walsingham: Majesty. Please, dignity. Mercy.
وولسنغام: مولاتي. رجاء، كرامة. رحمة.
Elizabeth: This is no time for mercy, Walsingham.
إليزابيث: هذا ليس وقت الرحمة، وولسنغام.
You go to your traitor brother and leave me to my business.
اذهب إلى شقيقك الخائن واتركني لشأني.
Is it his?
أهو طفله؟
Tell me. Say it. Is the child his? Is it his?
أخبريني. قوليها. هل هذا الطفل له؟ أهو له؟
Bess: Yes.
بيس: أجل.
My lady,
مولاتي،
it is my husband's child.
إنه طفل زوجي.
Elizabeth: Bitch! (Cries)
إليزابيث: حقيرة! (بكاء)
Raleigh: Majesty.
رالي: مولاتي.
This is not the queen I love and serve.
هذه ليست الملكة التي أحبها وأخدمها.
Elizabeth: This man has seduced a ward of the queen,
إليزابيث: لقد أغرى هذا الرجل تابعة للملكة،
and she has married without royal consent.
وهذه تزوجت دون موافقة ملكية.
These offenses are punishable by law. Arrest him.
هذه الإساءات يعاقب عليها القانون. اقبضوا عليه.
Go.
اذهبوا.
You no longer have the queen's protection.
أنت منذ الآن لا تتمتعين بحماية الملكة.
Bess: As you wish, Majesty.
بيس: كما تشائين، مولاتي.
Elizabeth: Get out! Get out! Get out!
إليزابيث: اخرجي! اخرجي! اخرجي!
Get out.
اخرجي.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Shekhar Kapur: So, what am I trying to do here?
شيكار كابور: إذن مالذي حاولت عمله هنا؟
Elizabeth has realized,
أدركت إليزابيث،
and she's coming face-to-face
وقد واجهت
with her own sense of jealousy,
شعورها بالغيرة،
her own sense of mortality.
وإحساسها بالفناء.
What am I doing with the architecture?
كيف استفدت من المعمار؟
The architecture is telling a story.
إن المعمار بدوره يحكي قصة.
The architecture is telling a story
إن المعمار يحكي بدوره قصة
about how, even though she's the most powerful woman
عن هذه المرأة، التي، رغم أنها الأكبر سُلطة
in the world at that time,
في العالم في ذلك الوقت،
there is the other, the architecture's bigger.
يوجد هناك المعمار الأكبر حجما.
The stone is bigger than her because stone is an organic.
إن الحجر يكبرها وذلك لأنه غير عضوي.
It'll survive her.
فهو سيعمر بعدها.
So it's telling you, to me, stone is part of her destiny.
لهذا فهو يقول لكم، ولي، أن الحجر هو جزء من قدرها.
Not only that, why is the camera looking down?
وأيضا، لماذا تنظر الكاميرا إلى الأسفل؟
The camera's looking down at her because she's in the well.
الكاميرا تنظر إلى الأسفل لأنها في البئر.
She's in the absolute well
إنها في البئر المطلق
of her own sense of being mortal.
لشعورها بكونها فانية.
That's where she has to pull herself out
ومن هناك يتعين عليها نشل نفسها
from the depths of mortality,
من أعماق الفناء،
come in, release her spirit.
لتأتي وتطلق روحها.
And that's the moment where, in my mind,
وتلك اللحظة هي التي، في ذهني،
both Elizabeth and Bess are the same person.
تكون كل من إليزابيث وبيس الشخص ذاته.
But that's the moment
ولكن تلك هي اللحظة
she's surgically removing herself from that.
التي تنتزع نفسها جراحيا من ذلك.
So the film is operating on
لهذا فالفيلم يعمل على
many many levels in that scene.
العديد من المستويات في ذلك المشهد.
And how we tell stories
والطريقة التي تروي من خلالها القصص
visually, with music, with actors,
بالصور، بالموسيقى، بالممثلين،
and at each level it's a different sense
وعلى كل مستوى هناك إحساس مختلف
and sometimes contradictory to each other.
وأحيانا تتناقض هذه فيما بينها.
So how do I start all this?
إذن كيف أباشر كل هذا؟
What's the process of telling a story?
ماهي عملية رواية القصة؟
About ten years ago,
منذ عشرة أعوام،
I heard this little thing from a politician,
سمعت بشيء صغير من أحد السياسيين،
not a politician that was very well respected in India.
ليس أحد السياسيين الذين لهم احترام كبير في الهند.
And he said that these people in the cities,
أخبرني أن الناس في المدن
in one flush, expend as much water
بسحب المرحاض مرة واحدة يستهلكون من الماء
as you people in the rural areas
مالا يحصل عليه الناس في المناطق الريفية
don't get for your family for two days.
في يومين.
That struck a chord, and I said, "That's true."
لقد لامس هذا وترا، وقلت، "هذا صحيح."
I went to see a friend of mine,
لقد ذهبت لرؤية أحد أصدقائي،
and he made me wait
وقد جعلني أنتظر
in his apartment in Malabar Hill
في شقته في مالبار هيل
on the twentieth floor,
في الطابق العشرين،
which is a really, really upmarket area in Mumbai.
وهي منطقة راقية في مومباي.
And he was having a shower for 20 minutes.
وقد استمر حمامه لمدة 20 دقيقة.
I got bored and left, and as I drove out,
لقد شعرت بالملل ورحلت، وعندما كنت في سيارتي مغادرا
I drove past the slums of Bombay,
مررت بأحد الأحياء الفقيرة في مومباي،
as you always do,
كما تفعلون دائما،
and I saw lines and lines in the hot midday sun
ورأيت العديد من المصطفين تحت شمس الظهيرة الحارقة
of women and children with buckets
من النساء والأطفال يحملون الدلاء
waiting for a tanker
وينتظرون صهريج المياه
to come and give them water.
ليصل ويعطيهم الماء.
And an idea started to develop.
وهناك بدأت فكرة بالتطور.
So how does that become a story?
كيف نجعل من هذا قصة؟
I suddenly realized that we are heading towards disaster.
أدركت فجأة أننا نتجه نحو كارثة.
So my next film is called "Paani"
إذن فيلمي القادم سيكون بعنوان "بآني"
which means water.
بمعنى ماء.
And now, out of the mythology of that,
والآن من الأسطورة المتعلقة بذلك،
I'm starting to create a world.
بدأت بخلق عالم.
What kind of world do I create,
ما نوع العالم الذي أخلقه،
and where does the idea, the design of that come?
ومن أين جاءت الفكرة، ومن أين جاء التصميم؟
So, in my mind, in the future,
إذن تخيلت في المستقبل،
they started to build flyovers.
أنهم بدؤوا ببناء ممرات علوية.
You understand flyovers? Yeah?
تعرفون الممرات العلوية؟ أجل؟
They started to build flyovers
بدأوا ببناء الممرات العلوية
to get from A to B faster,
للانتقال من نقطة إلى أخرى بسرعة،
but they effectively went from one area of relative wealth
ولكنهم بدأوا بربط المناطق الثرية
to another area of relative wealth.
بمناطق ثرية أخرى.
And then what they did was
وما فعلوه كان
they created a city above the flyovers.
أنهم أوجدوا مدينة فوق الممرات العلوية.
And the rich people moved to the upper city
وهكذا انتقل الأغنياء إلى المدينة العليا
and left the poorer people in the lower cities,
وترك الفقراء في المدن في الأسفل،
about 10 to 12 percent of the people
حوالي 10 إلى 12 بالمائة من الناس
have moved to the upper city.
انتقلوا للعيش في المدينة العلوية.
Now, where does this upper city and lower city come?
الآن من أين جاءت فكرة المدينة العلوية والمدينة السفلية؟
There's a mythology in India about --
هناك أسطورة هندية حول
where they say, and I'll say it in Hindi,
حيث يقولون وسأقولها بالهندية،
[Hindi]
(هنديه)
Right. What does that mean?
تمام. ماذا يعني ذلك؟
It says that the rich are always sitting on the shoulders
انا أقول أن الأغنياء يتربعون على أكتاف
and survive on the shoulders of the poor.
ويعتاشون من أكتاف الفقراء.
So, from that mythology, the upper city and lower city come.
وعليه، من تلك الأسطورة، تأتي فكرة المدينة العلوية والسفلية.
So the design has a story.
إذن للتصميم قصة.
And now, what happens is that the people of the upper city,
والآن ما يحصل هو أن الناس القاطنين في المدينة العليا
they suck up all the water.
يشفطون الماء كله.
Remember the word I said, suck up.
تذكروا الكلمة التي قلتها، يشفطون.
They suck up all the water, keep to themselves,
يشفطون كل الماء، ليحفظوا حياتهم،
and they drip feed the lower city.
ويسقون المدينة السفلى بالتنقيط.
And if there's any revolution, they cut off the water.
وإذا حصلت أية ثورة، فإنهم يقطعون الإمداد بالمياه.
And, because democracy still exists,
ولأن الديمقراطية مستمرة،
there's a democratic way in which you say
هناك طريقة ديمقراطية تقول من خلالها
"Well, if you give us what [we want], we'll give you water."
حسنا، إذا أعطيتمونا ما نريد، سنعطيكم المياه.
So, okay my time is up.
حسنا لقد انتهى وقتي.
But I can go on about telling you
ولكن أستطيع الاستمرار لأحدثكم
how we evolve stories,
كيف تتطور قصصنا،
and how stories effectively are who we are
وكيف أن تلك القصص هي في الواقع نحن
and how these get translated into the particular discipline
وكيف يمكن ترجمتها من خلال تخصص معين،
that I am in, which is film.
كالذي امتهنه، وهو صناعة الفيلم.
But ultimately, what is a story? It's a contradiction.
ولكن في نهاية الأمر، ما القصة؟ إنها تناقض.
Everything's a contradiction.
كل شيء هو تناقض.
The universe is a contradiction.
الكون برمته هو تناقض.
And all of us are constantly looking for harmony.
ونحن جميعا نسعى دوما لإيجاد التناغم.
When you get up, the night and day is a contradiction.
عندما تستيقظ، فالليل والنهار هما تناقض.
But you get up at 4 a.m.
ولكنك تستيقظ الساعة الرابعة صباحا.
That first blush of blue is where the night and day
والمسحة الأولى من اللون الأزرق هي حيث يجتمع الليل والنهار
are trying to find harmony with each other.
ويحاولان خلق التناغم مع بعضهما.
Harmony is the notes that Mozart didn't give you,
التناغم هو النوتات التي لم يعطها لكم موزارت،
but somehow the contradiction of his notes suggest that.
ولكن بطريقة ما فالتناقض في نوتاته يدل على ذلك.
All contradictions of his notes suggest the harmony.
كل التناقضات الكامنة في نوتاته تدل على التناغم.
It's the effect of looking for harmony
وهذا هو أثر تتبع التناغم
in the contradiction that exists in a poet's mind,
في التناقض الموجود في عقل الشاعر،
a contradiction that exists in a storyteller's mind.
التناقض الموجود في عقل راوي القصة.
In a storyteller's mind, it's a contradiction of moralities.
في عقل راوي القصة يوجد تناقض الأخلاق.
In a poet's mind, it's a conflict of words,
في عقل الشاعر، هناك تناقض في الكلمات.
in the universe's mind, between day and night.
في عقل الكون. بين الليل والنهار.
In the mind of a man and a woman,
في عقل الرجل وعقل المرأة،
we're looking constantly at
نحن دوما في مواجهة
the contradiction between male and female,
التناقض بين الذكر والأنثى.
we're looking for harmony within each other.
ونبحث عن التناغم بينهما.
The whole idea of contradiction,
إن فكرة التناقص برمتها،
but the acceptance of contradiction
وإنما قبول التناقض،
is the telling of a story, not the resolution.
هو رواية لقصة، وليس حلها.
The problem with a lot of the storytelling in Hollywood
المشكلة في الكثير من طرق رواية القصص في هوليوود
and many films, and as [unclear] was saying in his,
والعديد من الأفلام، وكما (غير واضح) يقول في حديثه،
that we try to resolve the contradiction.
أننا نحاول حل التناقض.
Harmony is not resolution.
التناغم لا يقوم على الحل.
Harmony is the suggestion of a thing
التناغم هو افتراض شيء
that is much larger than resolution.
أكبر حجما من الحل.
Harmony is the suggestion of something
التناغم هو اقتراح شيء
that is embracing and universal
شامل ومحيط
and of eternity and of the moment.
وأزلي ولحظي في الوقت ذاته.
Resolution is something that is far more limited.
الحل يتسم بمحدودية أكبر بكثير.
It is finite; harmony is infinite.
إنه محدود. التناغم غير محدود.
So that storytelling, like all other contradictions in the universe,
إذن فإن رواية القصص، شأنها كسائر التناقضات الأخرى في الكون،
is looking for harmony and infinity
هو البحث عن التناغم واللامحدودية
in moral resolutions, resolving one, but letting another go,
في الحلول الأخلاقية، بحل واحد، وترك آخر.
letting another go and creating a question that is really important.
ترك آخر وخلق سؤال بغاية الأهمية.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)